<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons viz. 1. A preseruatiue lilie to cure soules. And 2. How to seeke to finde Christ. Preached by that famous and iudicious diuine, Peter Lilie, Doctor of Diuinitie, and sometime fellow of Iesus Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
            <author>Lily, Peter, d. 1615.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05470</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108559</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844217</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844217</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9008</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05470)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9008)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1245:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons viz. 1. A preseruatiue lilie to cure soules. And 2. How to seeke to finde Christ. Preached by that famous and iudicious diuine, Peter Lilie, Doctor of Diuinitie, and sometime fellow of Iesus Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
                  <author>Lily, Peter, d. 1615.</author>
                  <author>Lily, Dorothy, d. 1627.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 65, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Snodham,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On Mark XVI, 16, and Luke XXIV, 5.</note>
                  <note>The name of the editor, Dorothy Lily, appears on A3r.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9008:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO SERMONS: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iz.</hi> 1. A Preſeruatiue Lilie to cure Soules. AND 2. How to Seeke to finde Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preached by that famous and iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious</hi> Diuine, PETER LILIE, Doctor <hi>of Diuinitie, and ſometime Fellow</hi> of <hi>Ieſus</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Except a man be borne of Water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdome of God.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Iohn Chap. 3, Verſ. 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Thomas Snodham,</hi> 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9008:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9008:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RELIGIOVS and Noble Lady, the Lady BARBARA VILLIERS: Increaſe of all Graces and Honours <hi>in this life, and in the life</hi> to come, eternall <hi>Felicitie.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madame;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing the importunities of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great and worthy Perſons will not ſuffer the Authour of theſe Sermons to lie hid in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuritie; I doe heere preſent you with a mite of his Labors: your Vertues iustly challenging at my hands richer returnes, then a bandfull of <hi>Lilies.</hi> Yet, as the learned and iudicious eye, will happly delight it
<pb facs="tcp:9008:3"/>ſelfe to beholde the reſemblance of the Authours face; ſo I trust your humble and religious heart will ſomewhat recreate it ſelfe with the heauenly ſauour of his gracious words.</p>
            <p>Let them that knew not his perſon, iudge his worth by theſe liuing Images of his ſoule: for they that knew him, do affoord him the testimony of a milde and humble ſpirit, fraught with all rich Iewells of excellent learning and knowledge. Of his vertues, what greater euidence can be, then the ſweet ſauour of a good name? Of his learning, what better proofe can we haue, then the admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble commendations of them who most excell in all excellent knowledge?</p>
            <p>O the admirable height of iudgement, and depth of learning that dwelt within the lowly minde of this true humble man! great in all wiſe-mens eies, except his owne. With what grauity and maieſty of ſpeach did his Tongue and Pen vtter heauenly mysteries? What ſweet ſtreames of ſanctified elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence did flow from his gracious lips? whoſe eies, in the true humility of his heart, were alwaies cast downe to the ground: all things that proceeded from his bleſſed mouth, were ſweetely breathed out, as from the ſpirit of Loue; ſo that the most famous Vniuerſity of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> once his nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing-Mother,
<pb facs="tcp:9008:3"/>giues this honourable testimony of him; That for Life and Learning, the whole world hath not many ſuch men. But what ſhall I ſay more? His praiſe is with God.</p>
            <p>J here then (good Madame) ſalute your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhip with this little Mite; knowing you to be furniſhed with many Graces; but chiefly, the ground of all grace, and nobleneſſe, true <hi>Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> which neuer takes offence at good-meanings: Therefore all happineſſe, ſhall euer be wiſhed to you, and all yours; by me, which will euer liue,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Ladiſhips, in all true affection,</hi> Dorothy Lilie.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:9008:4"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Chriſtian <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>REader, this Booke was pen'd with ſingle heart,</l>
               <l>But yet this Booke was pen'd with double Art;</l>
               <l>And therefore, reade this Booke with ſingle eie,</l>
               <l>And it with double honour dignifie.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="preamble">
            <div n="1" type="sermon">
               <pb facs="tcp:9008:4"/>
               <head>On the firſt Sermon.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe <hi>Lilies</hi> pure, delight in waters pure,</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Lilie</hi> pure delights in waters ſure:</l>
                  <l>And what theſe waters pure? Yea purest be,</l>
                  <l>The waters which the world doe mundifie,</l>
                  <l>The water of the Font, the pureſt ſtreame,</l>
                  <l>It is the head-ſpring of our <hi>Lilies</hi> theame:</l>
                  <l>The leaues of this our <hi>Lilies</hi> Booke doe grow</l>
                  <l>Amidſt theſe waters, whence all comforts flow:</l>
                  <l>Gather theſe leaues, and thou ſhalt comfort finde,</l>
                  <l>Theſe <hi>Lilie</hi> leaues will make an humble minde.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sermon">
               <head>On the ſecond Sermon.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MAny doe ſeeke, but few there be who finde,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe that many ſeeke, but out of kinde;</l>
                  <l>Now, that ye may ſo ſeeke, that ye may finde,</l>
                  <l>This Booke directs you, how to ſeeke in kinde:</l>
                  <l>Seeke not on earth, but ſeeke in heau'n for bliſſe,</l>
                  <l>For there is Bliſſe, where now your Sauiour is.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic">
            <pb facs="tcp:9008:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>P</hi>atterne of Learning, Patron of learn'd men,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E</hi>terniz'd be thy fame by learned Pen;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>T</hi>he
<note n="*" place="margin">For the <hi>Lily</hi> being white, is embleme of purity.</note> 
                  <hi>Lily</hi> notes thy ſpotleſſe puritie:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E</hi>mbleme is
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>For</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Greeke word for <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> ſignifies a Rocke, and is the embleme of Conſtancy.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> of thy conſtancie;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>R</hi>are are theſe Patterns for Poſteritie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>L</hi>earne then of <hi>Lilie</hi> (Chriſtians) pure to be,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi>t is the thing his bleſt Soule longs to ſee:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>L</hi>earne of this Saint-like <hi>Peter</hi> conſtancie,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Y</hi>e that with him will liue aeternally.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>
               <hi>Maria Lily</hi> moesta Authoris filia, haec ſecum maerens meditata est.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I Ioy that I haue found him whom I loſt,</l>
               <l>Whoſe death ſo many teares mine eies hath coſt;</l>
               <l>I loſt a Father, but haue found him be,</l>
               <l>A Father to the Church, as well as me:</l>
               <l>The Church yet calls him <hi>Father,</hi> ſo will I,</l>
               <l>His Workes doe liue, and he ſhall neuer die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Aliud eiuſdem.</head>
               <l>I Grieue that I haue loſt him, whom I had,</l>
               <l>Life of my life, who ſo my ſoule did glad:</l>
               <l>But doe I grieue, or am I rather glad,</l>
               <l>That ſuch a peereleſſe Father once I had?</l>
               <l>Yet doe I grieue, and yet againe am glad,</l>
               <l>That I ſhall finde in heau'n him, whom I had.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. L.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:9008:5"/>
            <head>A Preſeruatiue LILIE, to cure Soules.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Marke 16.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>He that ſhall beleeue and be baptiſed, ſhall be ſaued: but he that will not beleeue, ſhall be damned.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words are (almoſt) the laſt words our Sauior ſpake to his Diſciples: who hauing finiſhed the worke of our Redemption on the Croſſe, &amp; riſen againe a triumphant conqueror, laden with the ſpoiles of death, &amp; meaning now to aſcend to his Father; doth before his departure commit a ſpecial charge vnto his Apoſtles, and in them, to all others ſucceeding them in any part of that function, which charge S. <hi>Mathew</hi> in his laſt chapter expreſſeth in theſe words, <hi>Go</hi> (ſaith our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or) <hi>teach all Nations, baptiſing them, in the name of the Father, the Sonne and the Holy-ghost.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:9008:6"/>
            <p>This is the charge which Chriſt did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly commit to his Diſciples; but becauſe it was to ſmall purpoſe to lay this commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on them, to enioyne them the duty of preaching and adminiſtring the Sacraments, vnleſſe others would embrace their doctrine, and receiue their Sacraments; to allure men the better, and to draw them, for their owne good, vnto the diſcharge of this heauenly du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, he propoſeth a reward to him that ſhall beleeue and be baptiſed, and a puniſhment to them that ſhall refuſe to beleeue, or of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt reiect his Sacrament: The reward in theſe words, <hi>Hee ſhall be ſaued:</hi> the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in theſe; He that will not beleeue, <hi>ſhall be damned.</hi> Betweene which two eſtates, there is no meane, but eyther Saluation or Damnation: of which two my meaning is not to dilate; to ſpeake eyther of the Ioyes of Heauen, or Paines of Hell; theſe are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious Common-places: in which, as no man can want matter of diſcourſe, ſo no man is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to expreſſe either of them in the leaſt part.</p>
            <p>But my meaning is to ſpeake of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to whom the reward, which is vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueable, is promiſed; and to whom the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:9008:6"/>or threatning here belongeth: For this I take to be pertinent to the Time, and to this preſent Occaſion.</p>
            <p>I will beginne with the perſons to whom the reward is promiſed, ſet downe, in theſe wordes; <hi>Hee that ſhall beleeue and be baptiſed:</hi> In which words diuers things do offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to bee conſidered, and that which I thinke firſt is neceſſary, is the coniunction of theſe two: namely, <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Baptiſme:</hi> He that ſhall <hi>beleeue</hi> and be <hi>baptiſed,</hi> muſt be read without diſ-junction, and make but one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: For our Sauiour Chriſt doth not heere meane, that he which is baptiſed but beleeueth not, or that he that beleeueth, and is not baptiſed, ſhall be ſaued: but both are heere ioyned together, <hi>He that beleeueth and is baptiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Betweene theſe two, I meane, <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> Chriſt doth part the cauſes of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: yet let none miſ-take me, in that I ſay, theſe are cauſes of Saluation: I doe not ſay they are principall cauſes, but inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, adiuvant, ſecundary, inferiour cauſes, which it pleaſeth God to vſe and ſanctifie, for the ſauing of our ſoules. I doe not ſay, that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:9008:7"/>either both together, or any one of them by it ſelfe, is a cauſe abſolutely neceſſarie to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, ſo that he that wants either one, or both, muſt be damned; which in the latter member, I ſhall more largely declare; but I ſay, they are neceſſarie, in reſpect of our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and neceſſarie, becauſe commanded: and therefore, if of contempt, or groſſe, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected negligence, we either refuſe the one or the other, we incurre the diſpleaſure of God, and by that meanes eternall damnation.</p>
            <p>In this ſence I call them cauſes, and ioyne them both together, euen as Chriſt himſelfe doth; <hi>Hee that beleeueth and is baptiſed:</hi> both of them are, in their kinde, neceſſary. Of the one, that is, Faith, the Apoſtle ſayth, <hi>Without faith it is vnpoſsible to pleaſe God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.6.</note> Of the other, that is, Baptiſme, the Apoſtle ſayth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Titus</hi> 3.5.</note> it is <hi>Lauacrum regenerationis,</hi> the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of the new birth, and is reſembled by Saint <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.20.21.</note> to the Arke, in which <hi>Noah</hi> and his children were ſaued. The Arke was not a ſigne onely of the mercy of God, but God vſed it as an inſtrumentall cauſe to preſerue <hi>Noah</hi> in that great and vniuerſall deluge, and to it is Baptiſme compared.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:9008:7"/>
            <p>The ancient Fathers, grounding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vpon that, and the like places, doe ſpeake as becomes them, reuerently; reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Baptiſme to the red-Sea, in which <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi> that is, the Diuell, with all his workes, are drowned; and the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that is, the true Chriſtians regenerate, are deliuered from the wrath of God: To the Poole of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> into which the Angell deſcended at a certaine time, and ſtirred the water; and who firſt deſcended there-into, was cured of his infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie; I ſay, they not onely reſemble it, but preferre it before this water; for that wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter did onely cure the bodie, but this the ſoule: in this water but one could be cured at one time, there many are cured: into that water the Angell deſcended at a certayne time, and before he had ſtirred the water, it would not worke, and therefore it might bee called <hi>Fons ſignatus,</hi> a Fountaine ſealed vp: but this water is open and common, and floweth plentifully to all Chriſtians; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that prediction of the Prophet <hi>Zacharie: In that day,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.1.</note> there ſhall be a fountaine opened to the houſe of</hi> Dauid, <hi>and to the houſe of Ieruſalem, for ſinne and for vncleanneſſe.</hi> In
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:9008:8"/>that water God did worke by the miniſterie of an Angell, heere he worketh by the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of ſinfull men, yet is the effect won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull, neither doth our humility derogate from the power and operation of it.</p>
            <p>I might repeate many other their ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes to this purpoſe: many ſpeeches they haue, which ſome thinke to be Hyperboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and beyond the truth; but indeed, they are no more, then the Scripture teacheth: A man may as well aſcribe too little, as too much to the Sacrament; and as the Papiſts haue erred in <hi>Superstition,</hi> ſo ſome perhaps in <hi>Prophaneneſſe,</hi> to which theſe our times do too much incline: A meane may be held betweene both, that is, to thinke of theſe as they are in effect, cauſes and inſtruments by which Chriſt doth deriue into our ſoules the efficacie of his precious bloud: <hi>He that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth and is baptiſed ſhall be ſaued.</hi> And this is the firſt thing I thought meete to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, I meane the coniunction of theſe two, <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Baptiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, is nothing elſe (will ſome ſay) requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to Saluation? Is it ſufficient to beleeue and be baptiſed? VVill theſe two, without
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9008:8"/>good-workes, bring them that are come to yeares of diſcretion, to heauen? God forbid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhould think ſo: yet ſome in former times haue beene of that minde: who held, that <hi>Faith</hi> without <hi>Workes</hi> was ſufficient to Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and againſt that hereſie Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> hath written a whole Booke very learnedly.</p>
            <p>Our Aduerſaries of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> doe aſcribe vnto vs this errour, and ſay, that we haue reuiued this Hereſie: wherein, their conſcience tells them, they doe vs wrong: It may be, you haue heard ſome ſay, that Faith onely is neceſſary to Iuſtification, and that is very true; but did you euer heare any ſay, that onely Faith was neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation? I ſuppoſe there was neuer any ſo madde, as once to thinke it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in this poynt, doth vs right, who ſayth, That both they and wee doe hold a neceſſity of workes, though in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſence: They hold in workes, <hi>neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem efficientiae,</hi> a neceſſitie of the efficacie of workes: we holde <hi>neceſsitatem praeſentiae,</hi> a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of the preſence of workes: In plaine termes, the Queſtion betweene vs, is not, of the neceſſitie of workes, but of the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:9008:9"/>and dignity of workes, in which there is ſome difference betweene vs; but the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of workes is held of both: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is no need to refuſe the words: he is ſuppoſed to be in the wrong, which taketh away the neceſſity of a vertuous life, it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther requireth a reall refutation.</p>
            <p>For although it is confeſſed on both ſides, I meane, of Proteſtants and Papiſts, that good workes are neceſſary to ſaluation; yet, in eyther Religion, many there are, who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow the confeſſion of their faith, with the notorious ſins of their liues, profeſſing they know God, but denying him with their workes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16.</note> as the Apoſtle ſaith: and that is a kinde of indirect and implicite Atheiſme. How true this is, the times doe teſtifie, and I ſhall eaſily make knowne, yet not without griefe, as one that taketh ſmall delight in this diſcourſe, and yet not without profit, for I ſee a profitable vſe of it.</p>
            <p>I will beginne then with our Aduerſaries, who in contention do iuſtify themſelues and lay heauy imputations vpon others: but as the old ſaying is, <hi>Hee that condemnes another, ought not himſelfe to be faultie.</hi> Let vs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:9008:9"/>then their demeanour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> amongſt other notes of the Church, ſaith, that <hi>Sanctitas doctrinae,</hi> Pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of doctrine, both concerning Faith and Manners, is a ſpeciall one; and another is, <hi>Sanctitas vitae,</hi> Holineſſe of life, at the leaſt, in the authors and founders of their ſeuerall Orders: But if you ſhould meaſure truth, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſome of their doctrine taught, or by the practiſe of ſome of their Profeſſours, it would goe hard with them.</p>
            <p>In the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> amongſt other things, they haue eſtabliſhed Inuocation of <hi>Saints,</hi> and worſhipping of <hi>Reliques:</hi> in which Councell notwithſtanding, the Fathers aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled giue great charges to their Prieſts, that no ſuperſtition of idolatry be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in eyther of them: whereby they plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſe, that whatſoeuer they teach, the practiſe of the vulgar is full of corruption &amp; ſuperſtition: and that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth intreat, that the weakneſſe or ignorance of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort, do not preiudice the truth of their doctrine, vſing certaine words of Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> in a like caſe: <hi>Noui multos ſimulacrorum adoratores, &amp;c.</hi> Many ſuperſtitions are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:9008:10"/>by the vulgar, out of ignorance and weakeneſſe.</p>
            <p>But if wee ſhould come now from matter of Opinion, to the matter of Life, and alledge thoſe things which <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpoke, of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the Church in his time, and that which <hi>Petrarch,</hi> and ſundry others haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, it will make our haire ſtand vpright, and I do abſtain from particular reciting of them; neyther is it my meaning in thus cenſuring them, to iuſtifie our ſelues; for I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that the ſcandalous demeanour of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſſolute Proteſtants, doth make many a Papiſt, and that the vnchriſtian carriage of either ſort, doth make many an Atheiſt: and therefore both ſorts ſhould ioyne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to redeeme our Chriſtian profeſſion from theſe ſcandalous imputations, with which diuers doe too truely taxe vs, and to adorne our calling with good-workes, that the Name of God be not blaſphemed by vs, and that the mouthes of our enimies may be ſtopped. This is the beſt way to confute the ſuppoſed opinion, which taketh away the neceſſity of good life; that is, not by VVords, but by VVorkes:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.16</note> 
               <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:9008:10"/>men,</hi> ſayth our Sauiour, <hi>that they mayſee your good workes, and glorifie your Father which is in heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you will reply and ſay: Are not the words of your Text plaine? Doth not Chriſt ſay, <hi>He that beleeueth, and is baptiſed, ſhall be ſaued?</hi> I aunſwere, that vnder theſe two are comprehended good-workes; without which, <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>Baptiſme</hi> is to ſmall purpoſe. The diuels are not altogether without <hi>Faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iac.</hi> 2.19.</note> for they beleeue and tremble. <hi>Simon Magus</hi> had both theſe, <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Baptiſme:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8.13.</note> Of his Baptiſme, there can be no queſtion; for it is plainely ſet downe in expreſſe tearmes: and why ſhould any make doubt of his faith? for Saint <hi>Luke</hi> doth not onely ſay, <hi>He belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,</hi> but he ſaith it with an emphaſis, now <hi>Simon</hi> himſelfe alſo beleeued, that great ſorcerer, that notable Impoſtor; and that which is more, that he with others beleeued: And therefore, vnleſſe we thinke that all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were hypocrites, and that Saint <hi>Luke</hi> were deceiued in them all, wee muſt needes thinke that <hi>Simon Magus</hi> beleeued and was baptiſed; for both doth the Euangeliſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme; yet his end (as is thought) was moſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:9008:11"/>miſerable and damnable: and therfore <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Baptiſme</hi> without good-workes, profite not: Nay, it is certaine, that both theſe, I meane, <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> without good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes, when we grow vp to yeares of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, doe but increaſe our damnation, ſo farre are they from procuring our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>For it is better neuer to haue knowne the way of God,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21.</note> then after they haue knowne it, to turne from the holy Commaundement giuen vnto them. In Baptiſme we bind our ſelues to the ſeruice of God; God contracts with vs, and we with him: He couenants with vs to <hi>be our God,</hi> yet conditionally, ſo <hi>wee ſerue him:</hi> VVe couenant with him to renounce the workes of the Diuell, and to contract our ſelues wholly to his ſeruice. True it is, that without this contract wee are bound to the ſame duety, for wee are his creatures, and in regard both of our Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Redemption, are bound to ſerue him; but yet by our contract in Baptiſme, we bring a ſpeciall Bond and Obligation vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelues for euer.</p>
            <p>For euen thoſe things which of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:9008:11"/>doe binde vs, if we binde our ſelues to them by ſpeciall Obligation, doe binde vs more forcibly. For example,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 28.20 21.22.</note> 
               <hi>Iacob</hi> doth make a vow, and promiſe, <hi>That if God would bee with him, and keepe him in his iourney, and would giue him bread to eate, and cloathes to put on, ſo that he come againe to his Fathers houſe in ſafety, then ſhould the Lord be his God; then of all that God gaue him, would hee giue him the tenth:</hi> To which duties he was bound with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a vow; but by this vow hee was double bound. The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> deſcribing a iuſt and righteous man,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.4.</note> makes this one note of him, that <hi>he ſweareth to his neighbour, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointeth him not, though it were to his owne hinderance.</hi> No queſtion, but if he promiſe, he is bound to performe: though it be neuer ſo <hi>nudum pactum,</hi> a bare and naked promiſe, yet is a man in conſcience &amp; honeſty bound; but if he ſweare, then is he bound in a greater bond: for theſe are two bonds of a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full force, the one of Oathe; the other of Vow; and it is a queſtion, whether is the greater bond. The Caſuiſts obſerue, that <hi>Obligatio iuramenti est voto firmior;</hi> the Oath is a ſtronger bond then the Vow, becauſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:9008:12"/>we ſweare by God, though the Vow be <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctior,</hi> holier, becauſe we vow to God.</p>
            <p>It is euident then, that the contract wee make in Baptiſme, which is as ſtrong as any Oathe or Vowe in the world, doth tie vs more ſtrongly to that duety which of it ſelfe, without any vow or promiſe, is ſimply and abſolutely neceſſarie. But let vs yet a little conſider what manner of bond and obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation it is, that by Baptiſme, wee bring vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ourſelues. VVe call this myſtery by the name of <hi>Sacrament,</hi> which is a borrowed word: for the <hi>Romaines</hi> in times paſt, when they preſt any Souldiers, miniſtred an oathe vnto them, of Fidelity, which they called, <hi>Sacramentum militiae,</hi> the Oathe of their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarie ſeruice; without which Oathe, they made a ſcruple to beare Armes. VVee, when wee take vp Souldiers, doe not alwayes ſweare them, but they receiue Preſſe-mony, which bindes them ſufficiently: And what thinke you of a Souldier, that after he hath receiued his Preſſe-mony, after he is admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into pay, inrolled in the Booke, ſhall forſake his Campe, without the leaue of his Generall, as many run-agate ſouldiers doe,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:9008:12"/>or perhappes, reuolte, and flee into the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Campe, or ſtaying in the Campe, haue, notwithſtanding, conference with the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie and (as opportunity ſerues) deliuers vp the Fort or Holde committed to him, as ſome in our times perfidiouſly and diſhoneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue done? Or, if hee doe none of theſe, yet, eyther of cowardiſe or contempt, neuer fights blowe, neuer doth any ſeruice to his Captaine or Commaunder? Doe not ſuch Souldiers deſerue puniſhment, greater then if they had refuſed to ſerue, to which, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, their alleageance doth binde them? So is it in this caſe: In <hi>Baptiſme</hi> wee receiue Gods Preſſe-mony; then wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to be his Souldiers, and by that my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, doe binde our ſelues as faſt as any vowe or oathe can tie vs: and being thus bound, if we be <hi>deſertores militiae,</hi> forſakers of our Chriſtian profeſſion, and become flat Apoſtataes, wee then are more guilty then if we had neuer contracted with God to ſerue him; which to doe, wee are euen bound by <hi>Baptiſme:</hi> and heerein, many of vs doe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers wayes infringe the vowe wee made in <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> fleeing from the Campe of Chriſt,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:9008:13"/>into the tents of Sathan.</p>
            <p>There are ſcene amongſt vs, God be than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, that renounce their profeſſion vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſally, yet many do daily ſlide to Poperie; which, as I ſayd, though it bee not a totall defection, yet it is an aberration from Chriſt, and that a groſſe one: But where Chriſtians doe border vpon the <hi>Turkes,</hi> it is no newes to ſee Chriſtians turne <hi>Turkes;</hi> theſe are Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taes and runnagate ſouldiers, out of Chriſts Campe: But though there be none ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, yet are there diſobedient ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, whoſe ſtanding is in Gods Campe, but they fight the Diuells battailes: Such are all notorious and ſcandalous ſinners, who may carry Gods marke in their fore-heads, but are the Diuells ſeruants in their actions; whom I wiſh, if any ſuch be heere, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and conſider what a ſhamefull thing it is, after that they haue receiued Gods Preſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, &amp; haue bin brought vp in his Campe, to bee at couenant with Sathan, Death, and Hell. Of all others, Hypocrites, as they are of the greateſt number, ſo are they in the moſt daunger, becauſe vnder pretence of fighting Gods battells, they betray the whole
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:9008:13"/>army to the enemies.</p>
            <p>And yet, I know not whether I ſhould ſay, that ſuch as theſe are of the Campe; nay rather, as ſome ſay, they are but in the camp, not of the Campe; not of the Church, but in the Church: and as S. <hi>John</hi> ſpeakes,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>Some ſuch are gone out from vs, but they were not of vs; for if they had been of vs, they would haue continued with vs;</hi> or if they be members of the church, they are but members of the viſible Church; in which there are Tares and VVheat, Sheep and Goates, veſſels of honour, and veſſels of diſhonour: but how they ſhould be actually members of the Catholike Church, which is the ſocietie of the faithfull, and the myſticall body of Chriſt, I cannot ſee.</p>
            <p>Our Aduerſaries, who will not graunt the difference betweene the viſible and inuiſible Church, ſay, that the outward profeſſion of faith, doth make one a member of Chriſts body; and that no internall vertue is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thereunto: but when wee obiect vnto them, ſuch ſcandalous and groſſe ſinners, and cloſe and hidden hypocrites, as lurke in the body of the Church, then are they driuen to their poore ſhifts: for they affirme, that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:9008:14"/>ſuch are members, though dead members of Chriſts body; theſe, ſay they, are dead mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: Others call them not members, but parts or excrements in the body, as all our nayles and haires are but corrupt humours in the body, like biles or inflammations: But how any ſuch ſhould bee the members of Chriſt, or appertaine to his myſticall body, is beyond my reach.</p>
            <p>For of the Body Chriſt is the Head, who giueth life and ſuſtenance to euery member of it; men that continue obſtinately in any groſſe ſinne, are the members of Sathan; and how they ſhould be actually the members of Chriſt, I ſee not. True it is, that ſuch may appertaine to Gods election, and they may be called, as Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Electi ſecundum propoſitum ſuum;</hi> Elected according to his purpoſe; for ſo I ſee the Scripture ſpeakes; but actually, they are not the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, till they be called, ſanctified and bring forth fruit: neither can a man haue any comfort in Chriſt, either in regard of an hiſtoricall faith, or of Baptiſme, till hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and become a true ſouldier to Chriſt, to which his Baptiſme doth binde him.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:9008:14"/>
            <p>And therefore, if you wiſh to bee ſaued, adde to <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> Good-workes, which though in this place, they are not mentioned, yet are they comprehended. Neither can I giue better counſell to you, then <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> did to the people when they came to be baptiſed of him: For, when they asked him, <hi>what they ſhould doe to be ſaued:</hi> He anſwered, <hi>Let him that hath two coates,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 3.11.12.13.14</note> giue one to him that hath none; and he that hath meat, let him doe likewiſe:</hi> by which is not meant, that it is vn-lawfull for a man to haue two coates, but that which is redundant and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous in our eſtate, wee muſt giue to the poore; or, to ſpeake plainly, relieue the poore, if God hath giuen vs abilitie: it is in a word, a leſſon of Mercie, and that to be performed as time and circumſtances require: this was a generall leſſon which hee gaue to all the people.</p>
            <p>But when the Publicans came, who were infamous for their polling and oppreſſion, and asked <hi>what they ſhould doe,</hi> he bade them <hi>require no more then that which was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted vnto them:</hi> and when the Souldiers came, who, vnleſſe Grace reſtraine them, are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9008:15"/>proude, barbarous, and bloudy, and asked what they ſhould doe; he anſweres, <hi>Doe vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to no man, neither accuſe any man falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and be content with your wages. Vnum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, conueniens ſingulis reſponſum dabat:</hi> Hee gaue a generall anſwere to them all, and a particular anſwere to men of ſeuerall degrees and callings; and therein Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth his diſcretion: For there is a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall dutie, pertaining to all Chriſtians, and that is the duetie of Charitie, of Mercie; from which, neither high nor lowe, Prieſt nor People, neither rich nor poore are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted; euery man, according to his rancke and abilitie, muſt be mercifull.</p>
            <p>But there are alſo ſeuerall dueties apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to ſeuerall men; for wee all are one body, but in that body are diuers members, ſome appoynted to one office, ſome to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: and if wee will haue comfort by our Baptiſme, then it becommeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to practiſe all generall dueties with all Chriſtians; and particular alſo, with faithfulnes and deſire to diſcharge that duty that our particular voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth binde vs to, &amp; then are we truſty &amp; true Souldiers; then keepe we our vow made
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:9008:15"/>in Baptiſme; then wee may take comfort in our Chriſtian vocation: For, <hi>he that beleeueth and is baptiſed,</hi> and withall, bringeth foorth fruit, liuing anſwerable to his profeſſion, <hi>ſhall be ſaued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not deny but in many things we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend all; neither doth any perſon liue ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly and walke ſo innocently as his Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an vocation requireth; but God paſſeth by many of our infirmities, and accepteth our ſeruice, though vnperfect, when wee ſtriue to doe our indeuour, and haue a care of our conuerſation: Euen as a man that beares with many infirmities in his ſonne, ſo long as he doth not vtterly caſt off the yoake of obedience, and become, againſt all nature, treacherous &amp; incorrigible; for that diſſolues the bonds of nature, &amp; giues iuſt cauſe of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heriſon: ſo God ſuffereth and paſſeth by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ordinary infirmities, which humane frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie cannot auoyd, and taketh vs for his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, till by our hainous and groſſe ſinnes, and by our obſtinate perſiſting in them, wee fall from ſinne to Sathan, renounce our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and leaue our ſtanding: and yet when by repentance we returne againe, hee
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:9008:16"/>receiueth vs.</p>
            <p>Two things haue I now diſpatched, I haue ſhewed the neceſſarie coniunction of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Baptiſme;</hi> and that vnder thoſe two Good workes are comprehended: and now ſome would thinke, that I might conclude this firſt member, but I cannot yet leaue it.</p>
            <p>There is a myſtery of Iniquity, which was long ſince begot, in the time of <hi>Ignorance,</hi> and brought vp a long time in darkeneſſe, and neuer ſaw the Sunne: but now it is crept out of corners, and aduaunceth it ſelfe, with impudencie, in the open ſight of the world: it is a thing which men call <hi>Equiuocation,</hi> or <hi>Mentall Reſeruation,</hi> which ſome would haue huſht, and thinke meete it were ſuppreſt in ſilence: but we know the world hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of it; and it is <hi>lippis &amp; tonſoribus notum;</hi> it is talked of euen in the Barbers ſhoppe: and therefore we may ſay, <hi>Publiſh it in</hi> Aſhkelon, <hi>and proclaime it in the ſtreets of</hi> Gath: Howbeit, I would not deale with it at this time, were I not, in ſome ſort, enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced thereunto; for a ſpeciall Patron of it, is the Ieſuite, which peruerteth many Scriptures to this purpoſe, and doth not ſpare this that I
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:9008:16"/>now intreate of; <hi>Qui crediderit, &amp; baptiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus fuerit, ſaluabitur: Hee that ſhall beleeue, and bee baptized, ſhall bee ſaued:</hi> that is, <hi>if hee liue well,</hi> ſo ſaith he. Is not heere a men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall reſeruation, ſaith he? and ſhall I (intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this Text) ſuffer it ſo to be depraued? and ſhewing out of this place, the neceſſitie of a good life, ſuffer the Text to be wreſted to the defence of falſe dealing and diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling? No, I may not: and therefore I muſt needes ſay, that neither in this place, nor in any other place of Scripture, is there any mentall reſeruation to be found.</p>
            <p>Chriſt it was that ſpake theſe words, and that he vſed any mentall reſeruation, is moſt falſe. Saint <hi>Mathew</hi> repeates this charge or doctrine of our Sauiours more largely,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19.</note> 
               <hi>Goe teach</hi> (ſayth our Sauiour) <hi>all Nations, baptiſing them in the name of the Father, the Sonne, and the Holy-ghost:</hi> and he addeth; <hi>Commaunding them to obſerue all things that I haue commanded you:</hi> which word <hi>Nations,</hi> Saint <hi>Marke</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth, but <hi>Mathew</hi> plainely vttereth, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the fulfilling of Gods will, for that Chriſt commanded: &amp; therefore it is plaine, that heere is no mentall reſeruation vſed.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:9008:17"/>
            <p>The queſtion heere is, whether the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, which repeated not all the words of Chriſt, vſed any mentall reſeruation? No, for that which is neceſſarily to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, by the whole drift of the Author, and coherence of matter, is not reſerued, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it bee not expreſſed with ſo many words; which euen Boyes doe know; <hi>quod neceſſariò ſubintelligitur, non deest:</hi> that which is neceſſarily vnderſtood, is not wanting, or reſerued, but all one as if it were expreſſed.</p>
            <p>I heere appeale to one of their owne au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, who writing vpon this place, ſaith; that this very ſpeech of our Samours, <hi>Hee which belcoueth, and is baptized, ſhall be ſaued:</hi> And that of the Prophet <hi>Ioel, Whoſoeuer calles on the Name of the Lord, ſhall be ſaued:</hi> And that of our Sauiour, <hi>Euery one that asketh, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth:</hi> and in a word, all ſuch generall Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, haue a condition annexed vnto them, and that neceſſarily to be vnderſtood: which conditions, becauſe they are both in other places of Scripture clearely expreſſed: and that Chriſtian men are ſuppoſed at their very entrance to beleeue them; <hi>(for he that commeth to him, must beleeue, that he is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:9008:17"/>of ſuch as ſeeke him,)</hi> cannot be ſayd to be reſerued.</p>
            <p>They, I meane our Aduerſaries, ſpeake one thing, and think another, or reſerue ſome thing to their owne meaning, which is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for any man elſe to know what it is: But the Scripture ſetteth downe plainely all things neceſſary to ſaluation; for either they are there expreſſed, or no way; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to cloake their diſſimulation before men with pretence of Scripture, is to condemne the Scripture of inſufficiencie, to wreſt them to the defence of Hereſie, and to open a doore to Anabaptiſme.</p>
            <p>For if the letter of the Scriptures doe not containe the things appertaining to ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; if out of the words wee can not gather their meaning, then the interpretation muſt be left to particular reuelations without the VVord, and to this, doth this aſſertion tend, which by no meanes may be endured.</p>
            <p>I remember, ſometimes there was a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie betweene <hi>Ierome</hi> and <hi>Austen;</hi> two as famous men as euer the Latine-Church had; it was about an interpretation of a ſaying of <hi>S. Paules,</hi> where he ſaith, That he withſtood
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:9008:18"/>
               <hi>Peter</hi> to his face,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galat.</hi> 2.11.</note> which <hi>S. Ierome</hi> thinkes he did not; and that in ſaying ſo, he vſed a kind of diſpenſation: and thus doth <hi>Jerome</hi> ſay, to ſtoppe the mouth of <hi>Porphiry.</hi> But <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> writing to <hi>Ierome,</hi> tells him, that <hi>Paul</hi> in that very Epiſtle maketh this proteſtation,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galat.</hi> 1.20.</note> that he witneſſed before God, that the things he wrote vnto them, he lied not: and if he when he ſweares he lies not, ſhall be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, then muſt we thinke he withſtood <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> and then plainely telling, he did repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend <hi>Peter,</hi> and yet did not, then did hee abrogate this, and ſhew that he could not be beleeued in any thing; and that if this gappe were left open, the authority of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures muſt needes fall, and that no place, though neuer ſo euident, but might be delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. VVho, were he now aliue, and ſhould ſee Chriſt the Author of <hi>Truth, in whoſe mouth there was no guile;</hi> and the holy Scriptures the oracles of truth, wreſted to the defence of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, how would he exclaime at ſuch dealing?</p>
            <p>But if any ſhall ſay, that ſome places are darke &amp; obſcure; I grant it, and ſay, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it is ſo, (for, <hi>Ad edomandum la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore ſuperbiam, &amp; ad intellectum à fastidio reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candum,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:9008:18"/>cui inueſtigata plera<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vileſcunt:</hi> To tame the pride of man, to make him better eſteeme of the truth when he hath it, God hath wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped vp ſome places of Scripture in difficulty) yet, if we will ſpeake truly, the darknes is not ſo much in the Scriptures, as in our harts. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necaes</hi> wife had a ſhe-foole, who being blind, would yet not acknowledge it, but ſayd the houſe was darke, and therefore ſhe could not ſee: Such a foole <hi>S. Ierome</hi> ſaith himſelfe was, who for a long time could not reliſh the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but delighted more in the workes of Orators and Philoſophers, and <hi>when I was blinde and ſawe not the light,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I thought the fault was not in me, but in the Sunne.</hi> And ſuch fooles are they, who when they ſhould condemne the hardnes of their hearts, lay all the fault vpon the hardnes of the Scriptures. For as Maſter <hi>Luther</hi> ſaith: In ſome reſpects, all things are hard &amp; darke in the Scriptures; in ſome reſpects, all things are eaſy: They are hard to fleſh and bloud, for they cannot bee aſſented to, till God open the eyes of our hearts, as he did to his diſciples: but all things are ſet downe in termes plaine inough, ſo we vſe diligence to vnderſtand them. I ſay all
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:9008:19"/>things, all the myſteries of Religion, without (as they call it) any mentall reſeruation. Yet ſo beſotted are they with this fooliſh deuice of theirs, as that they ſtumble euen at the plaineſt Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>S. Mathew</hi> reports, that when our Sauiour cometh to iudgement, he ſhall ſay to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate; <hi>Neſcio vos, I know you not:</hi> and heere ſaith the Friar, Chriſt vſeth a mentall reſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein I know not, whether they are more ridiculous or impious. For Chriſt there alludeth to an vſual forme of ſpeech amongſt the <hi>Jewes,</hi> who when they miſliked a man, gaue him a <hi>Neſcio,</hi> that is, <hi>I know you not:</hi> VVhich form of ſpeech is vſed at this day by many: <hi>&amp; conſuetudo vocabuli, vita vocabuli: The custome of ſpeech, is the life of a ſpeech.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could our Sauiour more ſignificantly haue expreſſed his minde or purpoſe of reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting them, then in ſaying, <hi>Neſcio vos;</hi> ſo far was he from equiuocation or mentall reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
            <p>VVhen we tell them, <hi>Hoc est corpus me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, This is my body,</hi> is figuratiuely to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode; they ſay, figures are not vſed in matters of VVills, which ought to be plaine:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:9008:19"/>and can they not remember, how the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Iudges ought to be plaine? But theſe men (in ſome reſpect) may be pardoned; for, becauſe they, when they are cited, &amp; appeare at the Barre, doe equiuocate and diſſemble; they think alſo, that when Chriſt ſhall come to iudgement, and pronounce ſentence of ſaluation or damnation, he ſhal ſpeak doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. But God be mercifull to vs, and make vs of the number of thoſe to whom he ſhall ſay; <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father:</hi> For certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they to whom it ſhal be ſaid, <hi>Neſcio, I know you not,</hi> ſhall not only vnderſtand it, but feele it: they ſhall not neede a Commentary to know the meaning of our Sauiour, whoſe words they groſſely &amp; childiſhly wreſt to the maintenance and defence of their deceit.</p>
            <p>I am loath to wade further; and had not this violence bin vſed, to this Text, I ſhould haue abſtained at this time: and therefore I will conclude this point with the end of the 15. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> adding withall <hi>S. Jeromes</hi> obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on it. He in the 15. <hi>Pſalme</hi> deſcribing a righteous man, addeth, among other things, <hi>Who ſweareth to his neighbour, and diſappointeth him not, though it were to his hindrance:</hi> Such a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:9008:20"/>man ſaith <hi>Dauid, ſhall ſtand in the Tabernacle of the Lord.</hi> By which is meant, not onely him that ſweareth <hi>promiſſoriê,</hi> that taketh a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſory oath, but euen he that ſweareth <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertiuè,</hi> that <hi>formally</hi> affirmeth or denyeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing by oath. He that ſweareth, whether in promiſing a thing to come, or in affirming a thing paſt, ſhall ſtand in the Tabernacle, &amp; then he concludes, <hi>He that doth this, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be moued.</hi> Out of which <hi>S. Jerome</hi> inferres this: therefore he that doth, ſhall be moued. If he that ſweareth, and that truly, ſhall ſtand in the Tabernacle; then he that forſweareth himſelfe, that eludeth all others by lying and diſſembling, and ſuch trickes, as the Heathen man did abhorre, ſhall not ſtand in the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle. Sure I am, it is no way to get Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; the whole Scripture, from the beginning to the ending, in euery place condemneth fraude, lying, periurie, and ſuch like vanitie; extolling ſincerity, truth, plain-dealing, both in word and deed: this is the Lawe and the Prophets: this in euery leaſe is contained, &amp; thus it becommeth men, who are baptized in the name of the Father, the Sonne, and the Holy-ghoſt. God is the Author of truth, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:9008:20"/>thoſe that are of him, will ſay truth; the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell is the father of lies, and his children they are that practiſe that trade.</p>
            <p>And becauſe I haue tolde you, that there are particular dueties, giue mee leaue, I pray you, to be ſomewhat particular, as the Text, the Time, and this preſent honorable Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doth (in ſome ſort) require. It were a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie, or rather folly, to thinke it were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, to be both a Courtier, and a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. <hi>S. Iohn Baptist</hi> was a Courtier; for though he kept in the wilderneſſe, yet ſometimes he came to the Court: He was in good grace with <hi>Herod, who heard him gladly:</hi> and, could he haue flattered, he might haue obtained any preferment or honour in the Court: but he was plaine, and told the truth. He was not of his opinion that ſaid, <hi>Lex alia est ſolio, alia priuato,</hi> that which was adultery in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate man, could not be adultery in a Prince. <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Ezra,</hi> and many others were great Courtiers, in high fauour with their princes. How did they vſe their fauour? Surely, but little to their owne preferment, wholely to the benefite of the Church of God, and their Country.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:9008:21"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:9008:21"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:9008:22"/>
            <p>Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> reporteth of one who was the Emperours Nephew, and yet neuer asked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of the Emperour. It were to be wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that men of eminent place, great birth, and in high fauour, would know, that it is one part of their duty to imploy their greatnes to the good and behoofe of the Church of God and their country, and that God doth require this of them, as a ſpeciall duty. It cannot bee offenſiue (I hope) to haue admoniſhed thus much.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing, is that, which in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular pertaineth to women, who (for the moſt part) are the chiefeſt in this aſſembly, at this time, and if I ſpeake not to them, to whom ſhould I ſpeake? But what ſhould I ſay? <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> hath written many Bookes againſt the brauery of that ſexe: amongſt other things, he ſaith, That ſiluer, golde, and precious ſtones, were firſt found out by Sathan: and that foraſmuch as in Baptiſme they profeſſe to renounce the diuell and all his works, the ornaments and attire they weare, is againſt their vow in Baptiſme: But heere I am not altogether of his mind: For the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are the good creaturs of God, and may
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:9008:22"/>be vſed, ſo that the minde be not wickedly puffed vp, ſcandall be auoyded, and decency both in reſpect of perſon and condition bee kept. Yet in one thing, I thinke, women can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee excuſed, and that is in painting of themſelues; which howſoeuer ſome defend, the moſt religious and learned Fathers haue condemned. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſayth, that they which paint themſelues, doe (in a ſort) make Chriſt a lier: For, whereas our Sauiour ſayth, <hi>Yee cannot make one haire black or white,</hi> they haue a mean to make them all of what colour they liſt. Another ſaith, that when a Carpenter or Ioyner hath made a peece of work, he will not thinke well that any ſhould diſcommend it, or rend and deface it: And is it not a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, when God hath framed and faſhioned vs well, but wee muſt ouer-lay Gods worke with the diuels colours? How this may ſtand with your Chriſtian profeſſion, with your vow in Baptiſme, with the modeſty of that Sexe, I know not.</p>
            <p>I know that Figge-tree leaues are found out, to ſhadow this fault; but (in my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) it is but to lay colour vpon colour, to finde out Figge-tree leaues to couer naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:9008:23"/>withall: How much better were it for Ladies, according to the Apoſtles counſaile, to array themſelues with good-workes, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh ſomething of their brauery, that they might be better able to exerciſe the deedes of Charity, as <hi>Dorcas</hi> did? This (as I haue ſaid) is a generall duety, to which all of vs are bound, without diſtinction of ſexe or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and that by our very vow in Baptiſme, in which we are made Chriſts ſouldiers: For though women be priuiledged from bearing of Armes, and from the performance of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary ſeruice, yet Chriſts ſouldiers they are as well as others, and bound to fight againſt the VVorld, the Fleſh, and the Diuell; bound to ſerue God in the generall duety of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and in the particular duty which their ſexe and calling requires: And hereof I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you are not ignorant.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.18.</note> if any be ignorant, will at large informe them in their dueties. Art thou a Maide?
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.32.</note> 
               <hi>Be as one that careth for the things of the Lord, how thou mayst pleaſe God.</hi> Art thou a VVife?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>Submit thy ſelfe to thy huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, as is comely in the Lord.</hi> Art thou a VVi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe?
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Remember that the Widow that liueth in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:9008:23"/>pleaſure, is dead.</hi> Here a queſtion is moued, which of theſe eſtates is the beſt; but, (in my opinion) a curious one, and not meete to bee handled, eſpecially at this time: For they are all good, and commendable, each of them hath ſeuerall dueties appertaining; in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming whereof, they ſhall haue more honour in the eyes of men, more reward with God, then for al other the niceneſſes and trimneſſe of the bodie whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>But, to ſhut vp all in a word; as our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our doth promiſe ſaluation to him that is baptized; ſo heere on the contrary, he ſaith, <hi>But hee that is not baptized, ſhall be damned.</hi> Out of which ſome haue inferred, that <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme</hi> is not ſimply neceſſary to ſaluation: VVhich doctrine, although I take to be very true, yet is it not abſolute nor rightly colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted out of this place: For our Sauiour doth not in this, ouerthrow that which he ſpake in the former: and we muſt holde a coniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of both theſe, I meane <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> both being (in their kinde) neceſſary: yet, as I ſaid, not ſo, but that in ſome caſes one may be ſaued, without either <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>Baptiſme.</hi> Some haue no faith, and yet are ſaued: For,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:9008:24"/>what actuall faith haue Infants? Some think there is actuall faith in them; from which I ſuppoſe <hi>S. Augustine</hi> doth not much ſwarue: Others haue had Faith, but not Baptiſme, as <hi>Valentinian,</hi> and yet were ſaued: Some haue neither had Faith nor Baptiſme, and yet were ſaued, as children deceaſed before they could come to receiue Baptiſme: It is the ordinarie meanes of Regeneration, and therefore not to be contemned, not to be deferred; for how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer GOD is powerfull enough without meanes to regenerate, and bring to ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet thoſe holy meanes which himſelfe hath appointed &amp; ſanctified to that purpoſe, muſt by no meanes be contemned nor neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected: For, <hi>He that beleeueth, and is baptized, ſhalbe ſaued.</hi> VVhich fauour God grant vs all, for his Chriſts ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:9008:24"/>
            <head>Seeke to finde.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LVKE 24.5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Why ſeeke yee Him that liueth, among the dead?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He bleſſed and deuout <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> ſeeking our Sauiour at his Sepulchre earely in the morning, are encountered with this Angelicall checke; <hi>Why ſeeke ye Him that liueth, among the dead?</hi> A queſtion that might eaſily trouble perſons of ſo weake a ſexe, at that ſeaſon, and out of the mouth of an Angell too: But though they were amaſed at the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainneſſe of the voice, yet was not their zeale cooled from ſeeking him whom their ſoules loued.</p>
            <p>In this queſtion of the Angells are two things to be conſidered. Firſt, a reprehenſion
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:9008:25"/>of their errour: Secondly, a conſolation for their labour. Firſt, the reprehenſion and checke which the Angells gaue to theſe holy women, for ſeeking Chriſt among the dead, was not without iuſt cauſe, for it was an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious ſeeking. All of vs are ſeekers, and (in ſome ſort) ſeekers of Chriſt too; but, few of vs doe finde him, <hi>Becauſe wee ſeeke him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe.</hi> The errours then where-into men v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually fall in ſeeking Chriſt, muſt be narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerued, that they may the better be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded.</p>
            <p>The firſt errour men doe commit in ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt, is committed in the Time. The time aſſigned vs, for to ſeeke Chriſt, is the terme of this life; which opportunity, if we neglect, it is impoſſible wee ſhould euer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine our deſires, in finding Chriſt: For after death,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.26 72</note> 
               <hi>There remayneth no ſacrifice for ſinne, but a fearefull expectation of iudgement, and violent fire, which ſhall deuoure the Aduerſaries.</hi> Therefore the Apoſtle willeth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galat.</hi> 61.0.</note> that, <hi>Whilest we haue time, we doe good to all men, eſpecially to the houſhold of faith. There are twelue houres in the day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 11.9.</note> as our Sauiour teacheth vs, <hi>If a man walke in the day, he ſtumbleth not, becauſe he
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:9008:25"/>ſeeth the light of this world.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 12.35.</note> Walke therefore while ye haue light, lest the darkeneſſe come vpon you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It becommeth vs then not to looſe the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſeeking, and herein to apprehend the fitteſt opportunity. For though I will not deny, but Chriſt may be found at any time, whileſt wee liue, yet there is a difference of times; God is debter to no man: and if hee ſhould ſubtract his grace vniuerſally from vs, yet no man could iuſtly complaine of him, why he had done ſo: but God in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie doth diſpence his graces, and knockes at the doores of our hearts, deſiring to be let in: yet not at all times, but at certaine ſeaſons, according to the diſpenſation which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth fitteſt to himſelfe: At which time and ſeaſon, if wee harden our hearts, how know wee whether the like mercy will be offered againe? and therefore we muſt with all care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe embrace ſuch times and opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, when hee doth knocke at the doores of our hearts.</p>
            <p>The cuſtome of moſt of vs, is to deferre the ſeeking of God to our olde age, and to confecrate our youth to ſinne, to tender our
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:9008:26"/>decrepite yeares to God, and the crop and creame of our youth to ſinne and ſathan, not remembring the counſel of <hi>Salomon,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.1.</note> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth.</hi> Nay, do we not deferre the ſeeking of Chriſt to the laſt moment? to the laſt act of our life? And what can be more vaine? For, as <hi>Augustine</hi> ſpeakes moſt truely: <hi>Qui remittit poenitenti peccatum, non promittit peccanti vitam:</hi> God which promiſeth the penitent ſinner forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, doth not promiſe him length of life, or any certaine number of yeares. How many are cut off when they leaſt thought of it? Doth not the incertainty and frailety of our eſtate tell vs ſo much euery day? and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, not onely while as yet we liue, we muſt ſeeke him, but we muſt not neglect any time; yea we muſt with expedition accept any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of ſeeking Chriſt; for wee know not if euer hee will knocke at our doores againe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond error men commit in ſeeking of Chriſt, is in the manner; it is long ere wee beginne to ſeeke him, whom we ſhould ſeeke before all things; but when wee doe begin to ſeeke, it is after a negligent and careleſſe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as if the matter were not great whether
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:9008:26"/>found him, or no.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.33.</note> But what ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt? <hi>Seeke first the Kingdome of God:</hi> and by <hi>First</hi> is meant, not a priority in order, and the anticipation of time, but a priority in the earneſtnes or intention of our minde: as if he ſhould haue ſaid, Seeke the Kingdome of heauen, not onely before all things, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all things, with greater vehemencie and affection, then you doe any other thing in the world beſides. This is the meaning of our Sauiour, and ſo much doth the words of our Sauiour import: Hee that would finde Chriſt, muſt ſeeke him zealouſly, with fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and heate:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.12.</note> 
               <hi>For the Kingdome of heauen ſuffereth violence, &amp; the violent take it by force:</hi> And after we haue found him, then we muſt ſeeke how to keepe him too. To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>Tertullian</hi> hath a notable admonition; and very fit for our times: in which many are like vnto children,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>Carried about with eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie blast of doctrine;</hi> or like thoſe women who <hi>were euer learning,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.7.</note> and yet neuer came to the knowledge of the truth;</hi> euer ſeeking and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer finding, becauſe when they haue found, they looſe that they haue found; either of too much curioſitie in ſeeking, or of too much
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:9008:27"/>inconſtancie in relecting, and learning to ſeeke; of whom <hi>Tertullian</hi> thus ſpeaketh. Our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>Seeke, and yee ſhall finde, knocke, &amp; it ſhalbe opened vnto you, aske, and it ſhall be giuen:</hi> The true vnderſtanding of which place, ſaith he, conſiſts in three points; For our Sauiour ſpeaketh this, <hi>Jnipſis doctrinae primitijs,</hi> when firſt he began to teach, when hee was yet ſcarce knowne to his Diſciples, while as yet <hi>Peter</hi> had not acknowledged him to be the Sonne of God; and ſo moſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly, ſaith he, doth the ſpeech belong to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who did not acknowledge Chriſt to be the Meſſias, and therefore were willed to <hi>ſeeke:</hi> He addeth further, admit it be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to vs, as in truth it is, yet, ſaith he, it hath his bounds, and the true vnderſtanding of theſe words conſiſts in three points; <hi>in re, in tempore, in modo;</hi> in the thing, in the time, in the manner. The diuiſion is not much vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like that of <hi>Bernard;</hi> that is, ſaith he, we muſt vnderſtand what it is wee ſeeke, how wee ſeeke, and when wee are to ſeeke it: That which we ought to ſeeke, is Chriſt, and we ought to ſeeke him till we finde him; <hi>Et in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venisti cùm credidisti;</hi> and then thou haſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:9008:27"/>found him, when thou haſt beleeued in him; and then ſeeke how thou mayeſt keepe him; for no man, ſaith he, ſeeketh, but he which either neuer had Chriſt, or elſe hath loſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 11.5.</note> The man in the Goſpel who repaired to his friends houſe, knockt at his doore, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring him to lend him three loaues, was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry importunate to be let in; but as ſoone as he was let in, he ceaſed to knocke any more. The widdow that loſt her Groat,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 15.8.</note> ſwept the houſe diligently, till ſhe found it, but after ſhee once found it, ſhee gaue ouer ſeeking and ſweeping.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 18.3.</note> The widdow was importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to be heard of the wicked Iudge, but after ſhe was admitted to audience, ſhe gaue ouer her importunity; and therefore there is a meaſure in Seeking and Knocking: therefore, after we haue, by Faith, working by Charitie, apprehended Chriſt, we muſt not ſeeke after any other Faith: No, nor if wee will follow the policie of ſome States, not ſuffer diſputation in the queſtion of Faith and Religion; for though diſputing of truth be a kind of teaching of truth, and that truth feares no examination or diſcuſſion; yet as often as factious or ſchiſmaticall ſpirits ſhall
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:9008:28"/>offer diſputation in the matter of Faith or Gouernemrnt, to accept of that challenge, is to bring thoſe things that are ſoundly and ſurely ſetled, to new trialls, and to ſeeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that which is already found, which ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the rules of Pollicie nor Diuinitie doe admit.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake this, to ſtop the mouths of ſome, who with more inſolency then confidency, deſire, that things in controuerſie may be diſputed of; which, according to the ſence in which they deſire it, were to ſeeke for that which (indeede) wee haue found, and which without curioſitie or diſtruſting wee ought to maintayne, euen with the perill of our liues: As wee haue learned Chriſt, ſo let vs goe on, rooted and grounded in Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and not be moued from the profeſſion of our moſt holy Faith: Neither let vs giue eare to thoſe, who vnder pretence, either of truth in Religion, or ſincerity in Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, would alienate your mindes from that obedience and gouernement in which you haue been trayned vp in Chriſt Ieſus: VVee preſume, that we haue found Chriſt ſo farre forth; now our endeuour is, and muſt be, to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:9008:28"/>keepe him, not onely in our heads, by ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, that in our hearts, by affection; to which purpoſe, I ſhall ſpeake more in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient place.</p>
            <p>The third errour men commit, in ſeeking after Chriſt, is, that they ſeeke him not in the place they ſhould ſeeke him. This is the errour committed by theſe holy women, for which the Angels blamed them; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a little longer to be inſiſted vpon. And this error may be collected eaſily and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, from the ſpeach of our Sauiour in the Goſpell, who telleth vs, <hi>That falſe Christs,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.24 26.</note> and falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe, and ſhall ſhew great ſignes and wonders, ſaying, Beholde hee is in the wilderneſſe, hee is in the ſecret places:</hi> On which place, Doctor <hi>Stapleton</hi> writing, according to his virulent manner, ſayth, it is accompliſhed in our teachers, who lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the right way, the Kings high-way, the auncient and Apoſtolike Church, doe ſeeke after Chriſt in corners, in the wilderneſſe of our owne wandring imaginations, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſuch Apoſtataes, who challenge to themſelues the name of the Church: But the truth is, it is much better fulfilled amongſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:9008:29"/>them, who confine Chriſt vnto a certayne place, and thinke he cannot be found out of the limits of their Churches</p>
            <p>In times paſt, the viſible Church was in one Kingdome, I meane, among the <hi>Iewes: Notus in Iudaea Deus: God is well knowne in Jewrie:</hi> But now the time is come which our Sauiour ſpake of;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.23.</note> 
               <hi>The houre commeth, and now is, that the true worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in Spirit and truth.</hi> And this was long fore-told by the Prophets, and namely, the Prophet <hi>Malachy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mala.</hi> 1.11.</note> who ſaith, <hi>From the riſing of the Sunne, vnto the going downe of the ſame, my Name is great among the Gentiles;</hi> By which is meant, the calling of the Gentiles: And therefore, they are iniurious to binde Chriſt to <hi>Rome;</hi> and abſurd alſo, ſeeing in their Creede, they inſert theſe words; <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the Romaine Catholike Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, the Catholike Church, is the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall ſociety of all the Faithfull or Elect, both of men and Angells: the <hi>Romaine</hi> Church is but a particular Church, as the Church of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>France</hi> is; though (to ſpeake the trueth) ſometimes a flouriſhing Church;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.8.</note> of which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>That their
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:9008:29"/>Faith was publiſhed throughout the whole world.</hi> One of the originall or mother-churches: a Church (for her conſtancie in the Faith) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenced of other Churches: But now, the caſe is altered, <hi>The faithfull Citie is become a Harlot;</hi> Iuſtice &amp; Iudgement lodged in her; but now, thoſe that ſhined as gold are as blacke as pitch: And therefore, to ſeeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt in <hi>Rome,</hi> is not conuenient, much leſſe to appropriate the truth to the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> and yet I will not deny, but many in the <hi>Romaine</hi> Church appertaine to Chriſt, who grone vnder that groſſe ſuperſtition; &amp; Papiſme it ſelfe is not a totall defection, but an aberration from Chriſt, though a groſſe one: neither is there any cauſe, why they ſhould obiect vnto vs our paucity, who neither are ſo few as they would haue vs to be eſteemed; and yet if we were, we know that trueth is not to be meaſured by multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: <hi>Thou ſhalt not follow a multitude to doe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</hi> For the moſt part, euill goeth with the multitude: And <hi>Gregory Nazianzene</hi> ſaith, <hi>That to esteeme of things according to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, were to preferre the dust of the earth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Stars of Heauen; to neglect Pearles, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:9008:30"/>to gather pibble-ſtones, which are infinite.</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not (haſting to other matters) proſecute this point at full: onely this I wiſh you, to take heede of the confuſed clamours of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, in whoſe mouthes nothing is more frequent, then, the Temple of the Lord, the Church, the Faith, the ancient and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Sea, the Chaire that cannot erre, with a number of like childiſh vaunts, to bring vs backe vnto <hi>Rome,</hi> as if Chriſt were no where to be found but there, where indeede hee is neither ſo ſoundly nor ſincerely as he ought to be. I would alſo admoniſh the Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, who according to the praediction of our Sauiour, ſay, <hi>Heere is Christ, and there is Christ;</hi> and with them is Chriſt, &amp; no where elſe is Chriſt; euerie Sect challenging to themſelues the name of Chriſt, and thence excluding the other from any right or title therein. But this occaſion requireth other matter at my hands, and therefore leauing other errours committed in ſeeking Chriſt, out of due place, I come to that which is heere committed by the VVomen, and here I muſt repeate our diſtinction.</p>
            <p>The errours, ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> committed, in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:9008:30"/>
               <hi>ſeeking</hi> of Chriſt, are, in the <hi>time,</hi> in the <hi>manner,</hi> in the <hi>place:</hi> of which three errors, theſe women committed onely the laſt; for of the former two, we muſt acquit them: For how can they be ſaid to erre in the <hi>time,</hi> who ſo earely come to the Sepulchre to finde Chriſt? Chriſt was crucified on the Friday, the day following was the Sabboath, which cauſed them to reſt: but the day after, before it was yet light, neither diſcouraged with the darkneſſe, nor caring for the VVatch, which might well haue amated them, they come vnto the Sepulchre to finde Chriſt. Neither may they be ſaid to erre in that manner of ſeeking, which thoſe doe commit that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt in the Deſart, not for the Miracle, but for the Meate. Many there are, that are like vnto theſe; the Apoſtle ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>Omnes quae ſua ſunt, quaerunt: Euery man ſeekes his owne, and not that which is Christs:</hi> But theſe holy VVomen, when Chriſt was now dead, with the perill of their liues, (conſidering the malice of the <hi>Iewes</hi>) with the expence and coſt of their goods, come earely to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, intending to performe their funerall rites vnto Chriſt. And heerein (for their
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:9008:31"/>zeale and loue, though (not according to knowledge) they deſerue, if not commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, yet tolleration. The errour pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly committed by them, is their ſeeking of Chriſt out of due place: <hi>Cur quaeritis viuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem inter mortuos? Why ſeeke ye him that liueth, among the dead?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sepulchre or Graue, is <hi>domus mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuorum; The houſe of the dead,</hi> inhabited of rotten carkaſſes: in which it was vnpoſſible that Chriſt ſhould either remaine or putrifie. He tolde them, <hi>That hee would riſe the third day;</hi> which they forgetting, or not beleeuing, come with their odours to embalme him, and to that end, doe ſeeke him among the dead: For which cauſe, the Angell doth ſomewhat taxe them: <hi>Cur quaeritis viuentem inter mortuos? Why ſeeke yee the liuing among the dead?</hi> This is their errour, about the place; and ſo is it ours to, and much more groſſe: and I now ſpeake of the ordinarie errours committed, call them how you will, either in the manner of ſeeking; or about the place. Chriſt, when they did ſeeke him, was riſen, but he was not yet aſcended: but now heis both riſen and aſcended, ſitting on
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:9008:31"/>the right hand of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.1.</note> where wee ought to ſeeke him. If Chriſt be riſen, let vs ſeeke him where he ſits, at the right of God. But we, like wormes, lie groueling on the earth, whoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Conuerſation,</hi> ought to be in heauen. If you vnderſtand not my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, I will make it plaine: The Apoſtle tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing certaine perſons, among other things, brandeth them with this title, namely,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>That they minded earthly things;</hi> then the which, nothing is more oppoſite to the finding of Chriſt. Chriſt, as he is God, filleth all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; as hee is Man, hee is contained in one place; namely, in Heauen, where is the Kingdome of Glorie: where our affections, deſires, and thoughts, ought to be. For if we ſeeke him on earth, who now raignes in Heauen, wee ſhall neuer finde him. Men naturally looke vp-wards to heauen, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the beaſt looks downe wards: But is it not abſurd, that with the eyes of our bodies, we ſhould looke vp-wards, and with the eyes of our hearts looke downe-wards? Yet ſo it is: which he ſaith, is, to transforme the Image of God, into the Image of a Beaſt: and thus ſpeaketh he to him, to make him bluſh for
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:9008:32"/>ſhame: For whereas thou art made ſtreight, and oughteſt to looke vp to heauen; thou, with the beaſts, doſt creepe on the earth, like a brutiſh creature, &amp; ſo art become beaſtiall in heart, in the ſtowping of thy ſoule to the earth. If hee did thus ſay vnto them, doe not wee ſtand in need to ſtirre vp our ſelues by all meanes, to the contemplation of the heauenly life, and to ſhake off this earthli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of minde?</p>
            <p>The Prophet ſpeaking to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins thus;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>Hearken, O earth, earth, earth;</hi> three times repeated: May it not be ſaid to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of vs, who are nothing but earth? Earth in reſpect of body, earth in reſpect of our thoughts, which are onely occupied about earth, and earthly matters, how wee may make here and there a purchaſe, ioyning houſe to houſe, and land to land, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaketh, euen till there be no roome left. Some will obiect: Doe you condemne purchaſing? No: then were I very ſimple; I know that buying and ſelling are lawfull contracts, as neceſſary as eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are: But giue mee leaue, I pray you, to put you in remembrance of our Sauiours
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:9008:32"/>words;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 21.34.</note> 
               <hi>Let not your hearts be oppreſſed with ſurfetting and drunkenneſſe, and cares of this life:</hi> And of the Apoſtles words;
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 31.</note> 
               <hi>That they that vſe this world, be as though they vſed it not; for the faſhion of this world goeth away:</hi> VVhere the Apoſtle compares vs to Actors, and the world to a Stage, which muſt ſhortly be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued. Therefore we may vſe theſe things ſo farre forth, as they are helpes vnto vs in our ſeeking of Chriſt, but to ſet our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions on them; and for loue of theſe, to neglect the dueties of Chriſtianity, is heere to ſeeke Chriſt on earth, who now raigneth in heauen.</p>
            <p>I will adde but one thing, and ſo end this point; The Prophet ſaith:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 42.5.</note> 
               <hi>That God ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out the earth, and the Buddes thereof, hee giueth breath vnto the people vpon it, and his Spirit, Calcantibus eam, to thoſe that treade vpon it:</hi> which Text is diuerſly expounded; But Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi> among others, hath a notable Meditation, or rather, Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation on it. For, whereas the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Hee ſtretcheth forth the earth, and giueth breath vnto the people, and his Spirit to them that tread on it;</hi> his meaning is, that he communicates
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:9008:33"/>the graces of his Spirit, to ſuch as contemne the earth and earthly things. The heauen of heauens appertains to God, but the earth hee hath giuen to the children of men, who treade it vnder their feet. If then we would finde Chriſt, we muſt treade on it with the feete of our affections: I meane, contemne and trample it vnder foote, as we doe thoſe things we care not for; becauſe he giueth his Spirit, as the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Calcantibus eam, To thoſe that treade on it;</hi> that is, that doe not reckon or eſteeme it, but euen treade it vnder their feete, and contemne it: <hi>Qui amore Coele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtium, terrena contemnunt: For the loue of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen do deſpiſe earthly things,</hi> and all the wealth and glory thereof; to them, ſaith he, and to them onely doth God giue his Spirit.</p>
            <p>In this manner let vs liue on earth, not as men bewitched &amp; beſotted with the earth, but as contemners and tramplers on the earth; hauing our feete walking on the earth, but our Faith and Affections dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the heauens: being like vnto the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar, which <hi>Radicem terris, comam nubibus inſerit, Hath his roote deepe in the ground, but toucheth the Cloudes with his toppe:</hi> Or to the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:9008:33"/>Sunne-beames, which do ſhine on the earth, yet are they faſtened to the body of the Sun in heauen: ſo demeaning our ſelues on earth, we may inioy Chriſt which is in heauen.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I haue ſpoken of the Text as it is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſory; I will now ſpeake of it, as it is Conſolatory, to the women ſeeking Chriſt, and alſo to all ſuch, who liuing on earth, doe notwithſtanding ſeeke Chriſt ſitting in heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quid quaeritis viuentem inter mortuos?</hi> (ſaith the Angell) <hi>Why ſeeke yee the liuing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the dead?</hi> which words containe, not only a reprehenſion, but alſo a conſolation, of ſingular moment. For the women com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to ſeeke Chriſt, and finding the Stone rolled away, and the Body gone, (which is plaine by the ſpeech of <hi>Mary Magdalen, Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerunt Dominum; They haue taken away my Lord:</hi>) were ſore diſcomforted. The appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Angells in maieſty, as it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, made ſome impreſſion of feare in their tender hearts: which the Angels perceiuing, doe ſpeake comfortably to them; <hi>Feare you not:</hi> mixing (as I haue ſaid) Conſolation with Reprehenſion: For, without all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:9008:34"/>it ſounded ioyfully in the eares of the women, who being perſwaded that Chriſt was dead; and hearing the Angell tell them, that hee was aliue, <hi>that hee was riſen,</hi> could not, but be greatly comforted, when they heard, <hi>Quid quaeritis viuentem inter mortuos? Why ſeeke yee the liuing among the dead?</hi> You are perſwaded that he is dead, that he is ſtolne away out of the Graue: No, it is not ſo; Chriſt liueth, as before he told you: <hi>Goe tell his brethren, that he goes before them into</hi> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lile. VVas not this (thinke you) a comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſpeach to women oppreſſed with feare and griefe?</p>
            <p>The words then of the Angell were, not onely Reprehenſory, but Conſolatory: not to them onely, but to vs alſo, for whom theſe wordes were ſpoken. VVhat can be more comfortable then to conſider and know that Chriſt liueth? that hee is aſcended? that he ſitteth at the right hand of God in maieſty and honour? VVhen <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaw the Chariots which <hi>Ioſeph</hi> had ſent to carry him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 45.27 28.</note> he ſaid, <hi>I haue enough;</hi> Ioſeph <hi>my ſonne is yet aliue:</hi> But how much greater cauſe haue we to ſay, It is enough for vs, that Chriſt our head liueth,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:9008:34"/>that he is riſen againe from the dead?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.24.</note> 
               <hi>Except the wheate corne fall into the ground, and die, it abideth alone; but if it die, it bringeth forth much fruite.</hi> In which words, our Sauiour doth expreſſe the fruite of his Death and Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, which is, the reſurrection of all thoſe that ſleep in the duſt of the earth: for though <hi>Christus reſurrexit ſolus; Christ did riſe alone, who is the first fruits of them that riſe;</hi> yet not <hi>totus,</hi> all Chriſt did not ariſe: for hee is the head and we are his members, who are now raiſed in hope, and ſhall be raiſed, verily, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, in the time which he hath appointed, and liue with him, by the vertue &amp; power of that life which now is in him. It is enough for vs, that Chriſt our head, our brother li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, hee is Bone of our bone, and Fleſh of our fleſh: If the Firſt-fruites be holy, then is the whole lumpe holy. Neither is there any action of Chriſts, but yeeldes much comfort: For heere, he died for our ſinnes, and roſe againe for our iuſtification: but firſt hee was buried, deſcended into the Graue, which is, <hi>domus mortuorum, the houſe of the dead,</hi> where hee remayned, but yet as <hi>liber inter mortuos; as free among the dead.</hi> The wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:9008:35"/>did ſeeke him in the Graue, to which Chriſt deſcended; partly to proue vnto vs, the verity of his death and reſurrection; part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to ſecure vs, and to defend vs from the feare of the Graue, into the which (for our ſakes) the Lord deſcended: <hi>Jt is appoynted for all men once to die,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 17 14.</note> and then commeth the Iudgement.</hi> And wee muſt ſay with <hi>Iob</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wormes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.27.</note> 
               <hi>Thou art my mother and ſister:</hi> and to corruption, <hi>Thou art my father.</hi> But be of good cheare, Chriſt who was dead, now liueth; he that was in the graue, is now aſcended: now, <hi>Vltra non dominatur mors; Death hath no dominion ouer him;</hi> but he hath now the dominion of death. Hee did both enter into his graue, and ariſe againe, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure vs, that howſoeuer our bodies may pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifie in the Graues, yet God ſhall reſtore them againe; <hi>Et fragile hoc lutum in puriſsimam &amp; ſolidiſsimam testam excoquetur: This houſe of Clay ſhall be made farre firmer then Stone, more glorious then Golde or any ſuch corruptible matter.</hi> VVhy then are we afraid to deſcend into the graue; which, howſoeuer in it ſelfe fearefull, yet, to thoſe that ſeeke Chriſt zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly, as theſe women did, it is a bed of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:9008:35"/>reſt and quietneſſe, as the Prophet calleth it, or a Receptacle or Sanctuary againſt the troubles of the world? and ſo is it called,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 65.</note> 
               <hi>Eſay</hi> 65. <hi>Christ liueth</hi> (ſaith the Angell) <hi>and as a Conqueror of death, he is riſen from his houſe of death, and made it, to ſuch as ſeeke him, a repoſe, a rest, a treaſury, in which they are ſafely kept and ſtored vp against the day of Reſurrection.</hi> This is the benefit we haue by Chriſts liuing; by his riſing from the graue: As his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is for our benefit, ſo is his aſcenſion. <hi>Jaſcend</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>to prepare a place for you,</hi> to take poſſeſſion of Heauen in our name, in our nature: and here he ſitteth at the right hand of God, pleading our cauſe, and ſhall come in maieſty to iudge vs at the laſt day. A point worthy to be conſidered; and which (among other things) the Angell alſo meant, ſaying; <hi>Feare not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, as it pleaſed God, that an Angell ſhould publiſh the Reſurrection, ſo alſo by an Angell was the Aſcenſion publiſhed: for as heere the women are firſt rebuked, and afterwards inſtructed; ſo the Angell ſeeing them gazing and looking after Chriſt, rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked them in this manner: <hi>Whygaze yee you
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:9008:36"/>men of Galile?</hi> And then afterward comforted them and in ſtructed them, concerning the Reſurrection, adding withall: <hi>This Ieſus ſhall come againe euen ſo as you haue ſeene him aſcend,</hi> that is, he ſhall returne in the ſame nature in which he aſcended; which our Sauiour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſaith, <hi>is to be, in the glory of his Angells:</hi> But ſome may ſay, a fire ſhal go before him, the powers of heauen ſhall be ſhaken, and all the Tribes of the earth ſhall lament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him; how then doth he come againe as he aſcended? I anſwer; That though there be ſome difference in the circumſtances, yet ſhall he returne in the verity of his body, in the very ſame body, ſhape and members glorified, in the which hee was crucified: And it is a point moſt comfortable, that the Father of all mercies will vouchſafe by Man to iudge men, that the ſimilitude of Nature in ſo great feare and perturbation, might giue vs aſſured confidence. If then, his death, reſurrection, aſcenſion, glorification, and comming to iudgement, be all for our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, ſo that we ſeeke him heere, it is plaine, that this ſpeech of the Angells, hath both Conſolation and Reprehenſion. Theſe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:9008:36"/>had a ſharpe reprehenſion by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, for ſeeking him that was liuing amongſt the dead: but becauſe otherwiſe their zeale was good, God doth pardon their infirmity, and comforteth them in their miſery. As the ſpeech was vnto them, ſo is it vnto vs. I hope there is none of vs ſo perfect, but may very wel indure the Angell taxing our earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and ſtirring vs vp to the ſeeking of Chriſt, now ſitting at the right hand of God: and if wee profite by the reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, then appertaineth the conſolation vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, if we ſeeke him deuoutly heere. For the Prophet ſaith truely, <hi>Lord, thou art good vnto that ſoule that ſeeketh thee:</hi> neither is it ſaid, to that ſoule that findeth thee: for hee that according to his humanity raigneth in Heauen, by his grace reigneth in the heart; <hi>Et prope estinuocantibus ipſum: Hee is neare to them that call vpon him.</hi> VVe neede not (as the Apoſtle ſaith) to climbe vp into heauen, nor deſcend into the depth, heere hee is at hand within vs, if there we will nouriſh him, and giue him entertainement. The finding of him then, is not hard, ſo wee ſeeke him earely, whilſt he may be found; and all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:9008:37"/>on this point. And, that men doe not ſeeke him by lifting vp their hearts vnto him, I will ſhew you, both the reaſon, and the remedy, and ſo end.</p>
            <p>A man (ſaith <hi>Lactantius</hi>) is made, <hi>ex re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnantibus, of contrary principles,</hi> of a ſoule and a body; in reſpect of his ſoule, hee is of affinity with the Angells; in reſpect of the body, he is of affinity with the beaſts: the ſoule originally lookes vpwards, in reſpect of his body, hee is apt and prone to ſenſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie; of theſe contrarieties, there do ariſe in man, diſtractions of minde, the ſoule car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying him one way, the frailety of the fleſh another; and this warre betweene the ſpirit and the body, ſome doe thinke had beene euen in the ſtate of innocency, but that God gaue vnto <hi>Adam, Donum ſupernaturale, a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall gift;</hi> which was, <hi>instar aureifreni, like a golden Bridle,</hi> by which he might paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the ſtrife of theſe contrary parts, &amp; make the body ſubiect to the ſpirit, and the ſpirit ſubiect to God.</p>
            <p>But after <hi>Adam</hi> offended, he loſt, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that ſupernaturall gift (if any ſuch he had) but euen Nature it ſelfe was now corrupted.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:9008:37"/>He that before was prone to Senſuality, in reſpect of his body, was made ſenſuall and carnall in his very ſoule: For, as fleſh obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſpirit, may be called ſpirituall; ſo the ſpirit whileſt it obeyes the fleſh, is carnall: and in this eſtate of corrupt nature, man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but looke downe, his ſoule and body in reſpect, being but earth, fleſhly and ſenſuall.</p>
            <p>But it ſeemed good to God, to diſſolue the workes of the Diuell, and to ſend his owne Sonne, who both dyed for ſinne, and applieth the power and efficacy of his bloud, by the Sacraments, to the regenerating and renewing of the ſoule; which is purified from corruption and indewed with ſtrength and grace to riſe and mount vp vnto Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Yet, foraſmuch, as this renouation is not pure, but in part, there remayneth ſtill, and euen in the beſt of vs, this combate and contradiction, betweene the fleſh and the ſpirit, the ſpirit coueting vpwards, and the body hanging downwards: and as this <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus corruptibile, this corruptible body</hi> doth weigh downe the ſoule, ſo the ſoule doth make the body mount vp to heauen: And heereof proceedes our earthlineſſe; wee are
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:9008:38"/>made of earth, and ſo apt to fixe our mindes on the earth, vnleſſe the ſpirit vanquiſh this earthlineſſe in vs, whereon dependeth the victorie. For, as while <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> held vp <hi>Moſes</hi> hands ſtrongly, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed againſt the <hi>Amalekites;</hi> but when they fainted and waxed weary, the <hi>Amalekites</hi> preuailed againſt the <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> ſo while our hearts are ſet on heauen, the Diuell is van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed by vs, but when this heauy lump of Clay, this body of ours, with our ſenſuality doth weigh downe the ſoule, then the Diuell preuailes againſt vs.</p>
            <p>Therefore our care muſt bee to keepe downe and repreſſe, this ſenſualitie of ours, to mortifie the affections and deſires, and to make them obedient to the ſpirit, that our earthly affections beeing ſubdued, our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits with the wings of the morning may climbe vp to God, and in zeale of heart, ſay with <hi>Dauid,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalme</hi> 42.</note> Euen as the Hart deſireth the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter brookes, ſo longeth my ſoule after thee, O God:</hi> to which, there is nothing more auaileable then frequent meditation of the life to come, of Chriſts aſcending, of his ſitting at the right hand of God, receiuing of the Sacrament,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:9008:38"/>with ſuch other holy exerciſes of deuotion: which if you doe, aſſure your ſelues, you ſhall finde him, enioy him, and pray to him with much comfort in the Spirit; ye ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe with him familiarly, and take more pleaſure in him, then in all earthly pleaſures beſide; which are but vaine and momenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, blazing like a fire of Thornes, but ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly extinguiſhed: whereas the things that are not corporall, God beſtowes on his, whileſt, by ſetting their mindes on him, they ſeeke Chriſt aboue, whereby he brings them to raigne in glory with himſelfe for euer: to whom with the Father, and the holy Spirit, be all praiſe and glory, now, and for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, <hi>Amen.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
